# Anshita Saxena

Anshita Saxena

With over 6 years of experience (from ideation to production), I am a self-motivated, results-driven, and diligent professional, recognized with multiple awards at **IBM and Ericsson** for my contributions in machine learning, natural language processing, and big data. I am open to relocating anywhere across Canada.

## **Experience**

**Telus** Ontario, Canada

Senior Data Scientist - Generative AI

(Nov 2024 - Present)

Skills/Tech Stack: huggingface, PEFT fine-tuning techniques, python, pytorch, LLMs (claude, gemini, gpt-40, gpt-neox), linux, cloud, RAG, NLP, Git, GCP, prompt engineering.

Developing and working on LLM applications (RAG applications, function-calling applications), and LLM optimization.

#### **Ericsson Global AI Accelerator Lab**

Montreal, Canada

Machine Learning Engineer (Internship)

(Jan 2024 - Apr 2024)

Skills/Tech Stack: LangChain, Ray, fast API, huggingface, PEFT techniques, python, pytorch, LLMs (llama, mistral, openai, gpt-neox), multi-node distributed training, linux, cloud, RAG, NLP, Git, research, kanban

Awarded for best implementation at Ericsson Developer Conference 2024 for creating an end-to-end RAG-based QA LLM application. Fine-tuned and optimized LLMs for production on a distributed multi-node cluster.

# Hydroquebec Research Institute (IREQ)

Montreal, Canada

Applied Deep Learning Researcher (Internship)

(May 2023 - Dec 2023)

Skills/Tech Stack: PyTorch, JAX, Keras, multi-distributed gpu training, linux, research, machine learning, deep learning. Led a research project developing a virtual sensor using WaveNet-based deep learning to estimate high-frequency turbine displacements, achieving 89% signal overlap on test data. Implemented models in PyTorch, JAX, and Keras on 4M+ time-series data points.

**IBM** Bengaluru, India

Data Scientist/Big Data Engineer

(Apr 2018 - Aug 2022)

Skills/Tech Stack: PyTorch, LLMs(BERT, DistillBert, RoBerta), multi-distributed gpu training, linux, research skills, machine learning, natural language processing, deep learning, Kafka, Spark, linux, S3, Hadoop, Kubernetes, Docker, Databases (SQL, NoSQL), ETL processes, model building and deployment, Cloud (IBM, Azure), IBM Watson, GitHub, Trello, Jira, Confluence, Kanban, Leadership, Teamwork, Adaptability, Positivity, Creative thinking, SpaCy, Nltk.

- Achieved IBM Excellence and Eminence Award 2019, IBM Significant Business Impact Award 2020, IBM Service Excellence Award 2021, and IBM Growth Award 2022.
- Built an end-to-end loan prediction pipeline on IBM Cloud Pak for Data and Palantir in production, using PySpark and containerized ML models, and authored a white paper for senior leadership.
- Delivered PoCs and models in production, including a BERT-based customer support assistant and a revenueforecasting LSTM model with dashboard batch inferences.
- Developed microservices (containerized REST APIs) for high-volume data ingestion and NoSQL retention, handling 2600 messages/min and millions of daily requests in a multi-datacenter setup. Achieved \$2M in cost savings with automated data analysis and real-time tracking in production, using Python and Spark. Led a 21TB data migration on ScyllaDB with PySpark and Scala, ensuring data resilience across a multi-replication cluster.

# **Education**

Sep 2022 – | University: University of Montreal, Canada (MILA- Montreal Institute of Learning Algorithms) Degree: Masters in Computer Science (Machine Learning), Grade: A, GPA: 3.98, Category: Excellent Aug 2024 Courses: Machine Learning, Data Science, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing Aug 2013 – University: Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam Technical University

Degree: B.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering, Percentage: 82.26/100 [Honours (With Merit)] Jul 2017

#### **Honors And Awards**

2024	Celebrating Excellence Award: Organization: Ericsson, Montreal, Canada
2022, 2023	Diversity Award (Tuition Fees Scholarship/Exemption): Organization: University of Montreal
2019, 2020,	Awards: IBM Eminence and Excellence Award, IBM Impact on the Business and Significant Achieve-
2021, 2022	ment, IBM Service Excellence Award, IBM Growth Award, ScyllaDB Innovator Award
	Organizations: IBM India Pvt. Ltd, ScyllaDB (NoSQL Product Company)
2014, 2015,	Awards: Academic Excellence Award, Codezilla Coding Award
2016	Organizations: Meerut Institute of Technology, Meerut Institute of Engineering & Technology, MIET Group

# **Certifications**

Microsoft Azure Fundamentals: 2021, IBM Certified Big Data Engineer: 2020, Enterprise Design Thinking Practitioner, IBM Watson Knowledge Catalog Essentials, Cognitive Practitioner (IBM), Python for Data Science (IBM), Deep learning specialization (Coursera)

Link: Certification link

## **Publications**

2019

# Optimal Partition Search

A. Saxena and A. Saxena, "Optimal Partition Search," 2019 IEEE International Conference on Electrical, Computer and Communication Technologies (ICECCT), 2019, pp. 1-8, doi: 10.1109/ICECCT.2019.8869459. Link: https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/8869459

# 2017 DeepCoder: An Approach to Write Programs

A. Saxena, A. Saxena, J. Patel, "DeepCoder: An Approach to Write Programs," 2017 International Conference on Advanced Research and Innovation in Engineering (ICARIE), 2017 International Journal of Engineering and Manufacturing Science (IJEMS), 2017, pp. 9-13, Vol. 7, No. 1, Research India Publications. Link: https://www.ripublication.com/ijems\_spl/ijemsv7n1\_02.pdf